# 福建·漳州
Zhangzhou, Fujian
# 你看 咱们在汕头这一边吃过甜豆花
We have had sweet tofu pudding in Shantou
# 在重庆这边吃过豆花饭和豆花面
And we have also had tofu pudding rice and tofu pudding noddles in Chongqing
# 今天在漳州
We will have another food related to tofu pudding
# 我们再吃一个和豆花有关的食物
In Zhangzhou
# 走吧 看看是什么样子
Let’s see how it looks like.
# 豆花＋粉丝
Tofu pudding and mung bean noodles
# 调味
seasoning
# 卤味卤菜
Braised food and pickles
# 哇 这边有这么多的料
Wow, there are so many kinds of ingredients.
# 这个大碗和小碗 都是多少钱
How much for a large bowl and a small bowl?
# 你要加什么
What do you want to add?
# 加什么呢 加鸭肠和鸭胗吧
What can we add? Let's add duck intestine and duck gizzards
# 没有鸭胗了
Duck gizzards are sold out.
# 要豆花吗
Tofu pudding?
# 要豆花
yeah
# 除了鸭肠还要加什么
What else you want to add except duck intestine
# 还要加这个酥肉吧
And crispy pork
# 我们叫这个粉肉
We called this steamed pork
# 那就粉肉 鸭肠 辣椒香菜还放吗
You want steamed pork, duck intestine. How about chili pepper and cilantro?
# 都要
both
# 这个是11块钱
This is 11 yuan
# 好 支付过去了
Okay, paid
# 你看 这边的情况就是
You can see what's going on here
# 你点完豆花 粉丝还有自己要的料之后
After you order tofu pudding, mung bean noodles and some ingredients
# 还会放在旁边的电磁炉里再加热一下
You also can heat it with the induction cooker over there
# 这样的话 趁热会比较好吃
It’s more delicious while its hot
# 对 今天就是豆花加粉丝
Yeah, today is tofu pudding with mung bean noodles
# 但是它有个不同的点是
The difference is that, you can
# 里面可以加很多的辅料
Add plenty of ingredients in
# 比如说 鸭胗鸭肠
Such as duck intestine and duck gizzards
# 还有 像猪下水 猪皮等等
And pork offal, pork skin and so on
# 最上面铺的就是咱们要的料
On the top is what we ordered
# 中间就是粉丝
Mung bean noodles are in the middle
# 铺在最底下 就是一块块的豆花
Tofu pudding is at the bottom
# 豆花 一舀很容易碎掉
Tofu pudding is easy to break when scooping it
# 你想单独把它舀一勺下来 其实很困难
Actually it’s hard to get a scoop of tofu pudding only
# 所以说 每一勺几乎都是豆花和料的混合体
So every scoop is mixed of tofu pudding and ingredients
# 这一口咬下去 不仅有甜味 辣味
It not just sweetness and spiciness in one bite
# 还有豆香味
Also with bean aroma
# 它这个粉丝 粉条
This mung bean noodle
# 你看 晶莹剔透的
It looks crystal clear
# 相对来说 比较粗一些
Relatively speaking, it is thicker
# 吃起来一咬就断
It breaks when you bite
# 鸭肠好筋道啊
The duck intestines are so al dente
# 豆花粉丝 已经成了这边的一种特色小吃了
Tofu pudding with mung bean noodles is a local street food
# 因为这个本来就是漳州的小吃
Because it is a Zhangzhou street food
# 大家都吃的比较习惯了
Everyone is used to it
# 一天差不多卖两桶豆花
About 2 buckets of tofu pudding are sold everyday
# 昨天来的时候 都没开门
It was closed yesterday
# 我们星期一都休息 星期一都没有开
We close at every Monday
# 为什么会选择周一休息
Why Monday?
# 周一人比较少一点
Because fewer customers on Mondays
# 吃完了 我们走吧
Finished, let’s go
# 漳州特色手工麻糍
Zhangzhou handmade mochi
# 你要加绿豆吗
Do you want to add some mung beans?
# 可以
yeah
# 麻糍皮很Q弹
Mochi skin is very bouncy
# 因为是捶打出来的糯米皮
Because mochi skin is made by beating sticky rice with a stick
# 你好
hello
# 我是刚才司机师傅介绍过来的
A taxi driver recommended your mochi to me
# 然后他说这边的麻糍还有这个（停住）
And he said there is a mochi restaurant here... (paused)
# 你是雪鱼
You are Xueyu
# 对 你认识我吗
yeah, do you know me?
# 认识啊 我有关注你
Yeah, I'm your subscriber
# 好 谢谢
Okay, thank you
# 是买麻糍 菜头粿吗
Do you want to buy some mochi, or “caitouke”?
# 两个麻糍加白糖
Two mochis with sugar on it
# 等一下吧
Wait a second
# 小哥 门牌上的老陈是你什么人
Bro, who is the "lao chen" on your doorplate?
# 老陈是我爸
“Lao chen” is my father
# （心理笑）那你不就是小陈吗
So you are “xiao chen”
# 现在是你在接手吗
So you are taking your father’s business
# 都有在忙
We are both working on this
# 我爸妈和我都在店里
My parents and I are all working on this
# 他们现在是去休息
They are on break time
# 然后你看着店吗
So you are taking care of the business?
# 对对
yeah
# 他们说这边有个叫 黑眼睛 是什么
I heard there is a food called ”black eye”, what’s that?
# 这就是黑眼睛
This is “black eye”
# 它指的是什么
What does that mean?
# 就是糯米 艾草 加碱去煮的
We cook stick rice, mugwort and alkali together
# 然后里面有包绿豆沙
Inside is mung bean paste
# 但它为什么是黑的呀
But why is it black?
# 因为加碱 加艾草煮 它就会变成黑色
Because of the alkali and mugwort. Together, they turn the color black
# 碱 石头 然后一个咸
Alkali. Written as stone and salt
(explaining how to write the character in Chinese)
a
# 我很好奇 这个东西
I’m very curious about this
# 给我们拿一盒这个
Get us a box of “black eye"
# 然后再要两个麻糍 还有两个菜头粿
And two mochis and two “caitouke”
# 一共多少钱
How much in total?
# 不用了 不用了
It’s free for you
# 你要吧 你不要我也不太好意思
Please. I can't take it for free
# 不要 不要 不要
no
# 这边小吃 大约有多少种
How much types of street food you have?
# 店里 所有的小吃就几十种的
About dozens of street foods in our restaurant
# 我感觉好多
I feel it’s a lot
# 最有特色的就是这些用糯米做的了
The most special ones are those made from sticky rice
# 你要加绿豆吗
Do you want to add some mung beans?
# 可以
sure
# 这个皮很Q弹的样子
The skin of “caitouke” is bouncy
# 我们这个是纯手工打的
Those street foods are handmade
# 那种石头嘛捶出来的
Made by hitting with those stone
# 这种是皮会比较Q
The skin is bouncy
# 明白了
Got it
# 看我们今天是要的是菜头粿
And we also have “caitouke” today
# 还有麻糍 这个就是黑眼睛
And mochi. And this is “black eye”
# 很柔软 但是我感觉它长得很像巧克力
It’s soft, but I think it looks like chocolate
# 然后是 刚才小哥送了我们两个艾草粿
And the bro gave us two “aicaoke”
# 它看起来糯糯的 一定很好吃
It looks mashy, must be delicious
# 这个菜头粿就是用米浆、萝卜混合
This “caitouke” is mixed of rice milk and radish
# 蒸出来一个半成品
It's steamed first
# 然后再进油锅炸出来
And then deep fried
# 最后放上蒜蓉酱 注入灵魂
And finished with some garlic sauce
# 我想知道黑眼睛是什么样的味道
I want to know how “black eye” tastes
# 不知道 咬一口有没有什么样的惊喜呢
I don’t know, let’s see how it tastes after one bite
# 里面是包了馅的
There's filling inside
# 这边的麻糍 相对来说 还是比较便宜的1元1个
Relatively speaking mochis are cheap here. The cheap ones cost one yuan each
# 都是手工做出来的嘛
All are handmade
# 就是用饼皮 里面包上馅
Skin with filling
# 然后还在黄豆粉里 滚一圈
And rolled in soy flour
# 外面摸着很柔软 但是里面很坚强（里面硬脆）
It feels soft outside, but with a hard core (crispy and hard)
# 在这边吃这些小吃还是比较实惠的
It is affordable to eat street foods in this place
# 五颜六色的都想吃掉
I want to eat all these colorful foods
# 得赶紧走了 再不走小哥又要给我一些东西了
Let’s go. Or the bro will give us more free food
# 主要是怕吃不了 会浪费
I'm afraid of wasting. I can't finish them
# 今天就到这里吧 拜拜
bye